Anyways it is my great honor and privilege
to introduce Kirk McKusick. He is going
to give a talk of the history of BSD.
So this is actually a three-hour lecture
but I don't have three hours so there is
uh is this where I allow audience participation
The lecture is really sort of three
main parts
and what I’ll do is
describe the three main parts. Then everyone
will get to vote on which part they find the
most interesting
Then what I.. I won’t..
I used to just do just that part and I’ve got a
lot of negative feedback about that
So I’ll do those two parts don't get elected in
I'll just do quickly and then I'll concentrate
on the one
piece that
seems to be the most popular
so the history of BSD
This is BSD at Berkeley as opposed
to once it's out into the
open source world
So the first period of time is what I call
the Bill Joy era
And this is where Bill Joy is starting up BSD
and it's really getting it rolling and
so it ends when he
departs
and
Sponsers uh.. starts up this company
called Sun Microsystems which you may have
heard of
Uh.. Then the second part is sort of the heyday
of BSD. So this is the period of time
where everybody is
running is 4.2 and 4.3 and so on
and
during that period of time we were being funded
by DARPA which
deploy a microphone somewhere in this room
Uh at any rate
there was some very interesting
Uh.. battles that went on
Uh.. about
exactly how TCP ought to be implemented
and a lot of this at that history all
that all percolates out
and so that's sort of the middle period and
and then the end period is where we have
gotten religion and have decided that
you know maybe BSD isn’t going be at
Berkeley forever and if we want there to be
any
possibility for it to continue
Uh.. we better figure out how to get it outside
the university to people that
other than to the people that are licensed
by AT&T Bell Laboratories.
And so it's the whole story of
how we open-sourced it and fought a one lawsuit
about that and
so on and so forth.
So those are the three main parts.. The Bill Joy .. the
middle TCP
building years
and
the lawsuit years at the end.
So how many people are most interested in hearing
the Bill Joy years
one two three four five, six seven eight nine
ten, eleven twelve thirteen
fourteen fifteen
Sixteen. Ok.. how many people are interested
in hearing sort of the middle era
one two three, four five six, seven eight nine
ten, eleven twelve thirteen fourteen fifteen
Sixteen.. All right..
Seventeen eighteen ninety twenty twenty one
twenty five OK and how many people want to hear
the open
source
Lawsuit et cetera
Laugh.... Okkk
Do you see this is why I ask
This is usual it's interesting 'cause I get
different different groups votes for different
things
When I was in Japan they all want to hear
about the lawsuit.. you know.. that’s all they
have those in Japan.
Yeah that story is quite well known here
Infact the so interesting tidbit is that
uh through
Freedom of Information Act, California Freedom
of Information Act
uh we were able to get the uh
decision on that lawsuit unsealed so that
the actual text could get out which was
sort of interesting reading.
Okay, well for those of you who are interested in
a section that I'm not doing
This is where I get to make a shameless plug for
my DVD.
This is the entire three-and-a-half hour version
of this lecture
Which conveniently have a box of, so
if it's worth twenty dollars to you could
got one of these and walk away with it.
Ok. So uh unlike most of my talks and I don’t actually
have a laptop with slides on it and I just have these
handwritten notes
and the top line of my handwritten note says
the first four pages of this were written
on the Indian Pacific train on way to Perth
in January 1986 because I had
to give a lecture on the day I arrived.
So I have been uh told
that this was what my talk was going
to be and I was unprepared so
it's what a bouncy up-and-down handwriting
but it was the early history
so anyway
we're just gonna zip
quickly through
what BSD started at Berkeley
Uh by Bill Joy
uh Bill Joy was a graduate student I
happened to
share the same adviser with him, we were both
working on programming languages.
Uh you might find that hard to believe considering
that he did the C shell but
Uh.. laugh
at any rate up that's what we're doing and
So I shared an office with him and along with
three other graduate students uh
and
So uh I sort of was sitting there watching a lot of
this unfolding and in fact Bill was very good
at getting other people enthusiastic about
doing work.
There was his typical comment was.. “how hard
can it be, you could just knock this off in
a couple hours”
and usually you could knock off that one thing
but of course that with can you sucked
in and you know you end up writing the entire Pascal
interpreter or
the back-end or something
At any rate
Bill started doing initially just utilities
so was the C shell
uh that EX editor later
it also became the VI editor
the Pascal system
and say start packaging these things out and
sending out tapes to people and
then when
Ken Thompson who would
in an Alumnus of Berkeley
went out for one year's sabbatical and brought
UNIX with him
when he left Bill sort of took over running
the system what we would call a system administrator
today
Uh at any rate this got him interested in this the system
There were patches that were coming back
from AT&T he was putting those in and he was then
making some others sending them back to AT&T
and he
and
so
over time there were bigger and bigger bits of
the system and finally got tired of trying
to
track what other people's UNIXes look
like
and so
uh with the advent of FreeBSD the
third distribution
He just put together an entire package
uh and this was actually to the VAX rather
than the PDP-11 which is what we had started
on
all the 2.
versions of the of BSD
were actually worked on by the other people not by
the Bill especially not the stuff where
the kernel begins to become involved
2.9, 2.10, 2.11 et cetera
uh was actually done by
other people many years uh later so 2.11
does not precede 3.0
Uh 2.11 is you know contemporary
with 4.4
Uh at any rate uh
once we got the
uh the BSD
distribution out into the world
Uh it started getting used by a lot of people
because it
really
was a big step forward over what AT&T were
shipping
in particular
uh as we started getting things like
the TCP/IP networking
Uh So you had a choice you can run the AT&T
version which had UUCP as networking
or you could run BSD that had sockets, TCP et
cetera
you could run
AT&T's version which had a file system that
could utilize 3 to 5 percent of the bandwidth
of the disk
or you could run BSD which could utilize 50 percent
of the bandwidth of the disk
et cetera.
So many people would buy the AT&T license
and immediately drop Berkeley to add UNIX
on to it.
Uh consequently it was getting wide distribution
atleast in the university environments
Uh
And uh starting to sort of eek out into the commercial
environments
The commercial environments were not large because
commercial environments just weren’t using UNIX
at that time
for the most part
Uh So at any rate
Bill got it
Uh well
with FreeBSD coming out uh
The DARPA which is
essentially
puts out research contracts for
all the different branches of the military
Uh was
had a huge number of contracts
out with lots of different people being stuff
related computers and they all have different computers
and different operating systems and they were using
different languages
and so if one group would do something
they just couldn't really pass that
over take some other group that might want
to utilize it because this was written in
FORTRAN and that was written in PL1
You know this was running on
you know some deck machine and that was running on some
IBM hardware et cetera.
and so DARPA decided that they
really wanted to consolidate
on hardware and operating system
and then have people work there and so there's a
better chance if they would be able to co-operate.
So they put out a a sort of
call, essentially a request for
proposals or whatever they called in those
days
and
essentially there were two
uh main contending things that came in
one was the VAX
running VMS
and the other one was the VAX running
Berkeley UNIX
and of course
the uh the people that were promoting the
VAX running VMS
were arguing like well you know this is a real
vendor supported operating system and
you know that this not just some flaky students
at Berkeley that are doing it
then you know therefore this ought to be the operating
system
And that really put the final nail
on the coffin
Uh this guy named Dave Cashkin came up with a set of
benchmarks
Uh what we would call micro benchmarks
today so how fast can you do Get PID
and how fast can you do that pipe thing
When you ping a single packet back and forth to see
how fast you can contact switch
and
uh
showed that VMS did these things much faster
than BSD did.
and this of course
made Bill go ballistic
and
Uh besides saying that they were as stupidest benchmarks
he'd ever since he said, ""If that's the way
they're gonna decide then we'll just go
make those things run fast""
and it was sort of an interesting story about
other half and what
he got uh the BSD to run those benchmarks as fast
as the VMS
and
so
the upshot of it was that DARPA
was still sort of sitting on the fence
and Bill’s comment was well VMS we're stuck
with VMX forever
and you know may be some other computer might
be interesting down the road
and BSD is set up so that it's much more portable
uh you know it's tie. UNIX, in general is
portable across different architectures we've
already proved it by running it for n=2
so therefore
it's a proved point
so
at any rate DARPA agreed to that
and they put in some initial money to Berkeley
and the initial things that Berkeley was
really just
uh to come up with
Uh well we had out 3BSD
which had a lot of functionality but the
performance wasn't so great
and so the that first point was to get
4 BSD out
which was going to have
sort of that
that additional functionality they really felt
they needed
uh which were just
really small tweeks
Uh things like the ability to automatically
reboot after crash
Uh Job control
uh PRAM’s list which was needed by a bunch
of their uh folks, deliver mail, smoke in air
that was the uh the predecessor to
send mail
except without a configuration file you just
compiled and checked the way you needed things
that were
uh at any rate
Uh that came out
and that 4.1
so it nail that down cleaned it up
got the performance decent
and that fulfilled the first DARPA contract.
DARPA had put in something like
you know three-quarters of a million dollars or something
and boom topped this huge pay back from it
and
people seem to be happy with it
so they decided that maybe that the funky graduate students
at Berkeley could do stuff
and so then they put in that of
considerably larger
contract it was I don't know what three or
five million dollars
and this was a longer term
and in
those times he would get
for example a three-year contract
of which is sort of unheard of in lot of the
research stuff today.
So you could really sort of spend some time
figuring out what you can do and do it
for eighteen months to two years before you had
to start working about
renewing et cetera.
Uh in any way
the grand goals for this
Big contract that DARPA gave
was
Uh there were four pieces. One was
to get a
real networking end
uh at that time
Uh there was just NCP
Uh which was that
Network Control Protocol, the predecessor to TCP/IP
Uh a good file system in there
Uh restartable signals so you could actually
use them to drive work as opposed to just
terminating programs
and a new virtual memory system
Uh that wasn't
well essentially that allowed shared memory
uh that the one
the predecessor
that we were running BSD at that
time
shared the text space that would be only the part
of your program but all the rest
could not shared
So those were the four deliverables.
now for the kind of networking
they still didn't really trust us.
So they decided that what they were going
to do
was divide into two parts.
So they were going to get
Bolt, Beranek and Newman BBN
we are going to actually write the TCP/IP protocol
stuff
and then What Berkeley was supposed to do
was design the
programming interface
uh so
the socket, connect, except so on
and then BBN was to deliver
the thing that plugged in underneath that interface
and Berkeley was to integrate it into
BSD and uh
they would ship it.
and
Uh so
this all starts on and BBN gets to work
and
Bill Joy gets to work on the interface and
uh so
eventually what happens is that Bill has sort
of the framework of this stuff. And Bill being
Bill uh
he he worked rather quickly
Uh someone wants to ask you to compare myself
to Bill Joy and I said look
there's really nothing that he's done that
I couldn't do but the problem is
what he gets done in a year would take me
a decade
because he was the master of figuring out.
I'm here
that's where I want to get to
what is absolutely shortest path from here
to there
and he would do it
and you end up with code
that worked but
that was not maintainable, extendable, changeable.
Anybody looked at the old version of the VI
understands what I’m talking about.
so
So some of the rest of us you know
like to have stuff that like
you could go back and do something with later
but that takes longer
At any rate
Bill figured out this socket interface the first
draft of it it anyway
and he's got it and now he needs the networking protocols
to put underneath it
so he goes to to
Uh Rob Gurvitz who was
leading the program of
development of TCP/IP at BBN
and says hey I got the socket interface and I need
something to put in here
and Rob says well we're not really done yet
but we have we have this slight prototype code
and you know you could put that in it
see how that works in
you know then we’ll iterate
up so that we can work in parallel of you.
So Bill gets the code and
he puts it in
and
cranks it up and he gets a kind of working
then decides to run
Some full test between machines to see
how well it works.
And we’re running at the at that time our development
machines development inputs were
VAC 750’s
so that was the big honk at VAC 780
that ran an entire NIP
and then there were these much smaller things
that were merely the size of a large
uh dishwasher
uh its bigger than a dishwasher more like
washing machine yes
its over range at any rate and used about
as much power as the same.
Uh with all the burners turned ON assuming its electric
uh anyway the VAC 750 only
ran at 0.7 NIPs
Uh and so
Bill needs to be able to run some tests back and forth
between these machines
and of course we don't have
anything like FTP or TELNET
anything that, which is not written yet
and so he just
being Bill says well
I'll just hack up something
uh which was RLogin RCP et cetera.
which was really just the design so that he
could test running between these two machines
Uh
This is the legacy that we end up with and
why the protocol number or anything like
that in the header you know it’s just a
test program no one is gonna actually use this
so the uh upshot of all this that
Bill fires up
RCP and
to copy a file between machines
and
and it copies the file at about 56 or
60 kilobits per second
and at that point the CPU was pegged
on the VAX 750
And it you know
there's plenty of bandwidth still available
because we had 10 megabit Ethernet at that point
we had the new 10 megabit Ethernet because mostly
it was 3 megabit but
we had the 10 which was like really cool stuff.
uh and
uh so he talks to Rob Gerwitz you know this thing runs
and Gerwitz was his attitude
as well the backbone
of the only the 56 K so as long as
we can saturate that what's the problem
and Bill’s attitude is well no I need to be
all you know get closer to the bandwidth of
the network between these local machines
And so of course Bill being Bill dives in to see
why this is the case that it's not running very
fast.
Infact, he probably
wrote this
to some of this stuff to figure out
what was not running quickly. We already
had it for user=level of our programs that’s what we
put it into the kernel
And sad to say some of these tools are still like
considered
like leading tools but are not leading tools but
still used tools today
Uh which isn't to say bad that it's just that
seems like in twenty years you could do better
at any rate
he quickly discovers that way the TCP/IP
code is written
is it’s this elaborate state machine
and there's the state transitions that you
go through and
each time we want do a state transition the
you jump through an indirect
this and that and other things and
and he goes well you know this is just way too
efficient and you know
we could just take the state machine turned
into a giant switch statement
And you know there will be a few GOTO's here and there
when you need to switch states buttoning ON and that’s that
We'll just do that
And so he starts cranking away on this thing
and
pounding out all of that
the structure and getting a down
of what it looks like today
And uh
actually it's been cleaned up considerably over
the years but
Uh so he cranks it down to this and
gets up to the point where
he can at least saturate the 3 megabit wire
we can’t saturate the
10 megabit wire but it's because the
actually Ethernet controllers themselves are
not able to uh
really run at 10 megabits uh
these were you know prototype early release
stuff and so
we get it upto
somewhere around four
megabit uh
But we're only running at 40% CPU time
so in theory if we could have run at wire
speed we got up to 10 megabit
and for other reasons it wouldn't have
but
the point is we were like uh a way way, order of magnitude
ahead of where we started from literally
and so
Uh there's a lot of pressure from a lot of the
uh the people that have been that have 4.1
that they want to
try out this new networking stuff
and so uh
this code
as such as it was
uh got released as something that we called
4.1a
Uh so 4.1a was sort of the
first incremental release of
Uh between 4.1 and 4.2
and this got surprisingly large
larger distribution then we had really planned
on because you know you give it to one person
and then someone else hears about it. They want it
then someone else wants it nahnah.....
It's not like today and where you just put it up
and anonymous FTP. This was still
put it on a tape mail the tape to somebody, big
nine track tapes
uh
And uh if you'd want lucky enough to have a high
tape drive, a 6250
bits per inch drive then you had to get
the 16 in four
tapes to get all out there
Uh at any rate
This this code goes out
Uh and uh
measured about this time Sam Leffler
somebody's name probably know in contemporary
stuff having to do with wireless
Uh I actually joined
the CSFG, the group there
uh and
he begins to help build with
a rewrite of the networking interface
in particular
uh Bill hadn't quiet gotten on to the
fact that
uh When you may want to have multiple connections
concurrently on a particular port
so if you're running SMTP
service or HTTP
Uh the way he had written had uh except
that the that the what we think of a rendezvous
socket today was actually connected
and so that nobody else to talk to you on
that particular port to you. When you’re
finished with that conversation and then
that the sock would become free again and you
could’ve the next connection.
he says like that no
no we got it like
to have more than one at a time
and so that's when the whole listen and the
rendezvous socket works up returns to a new
connected socket and so on
uh and so at any rate
this this all gets done
And uh
I've gotten roped into doing the file system
which is another part of the earlier story.
uh and so the file system is sort of the
point where we're ready to inflict I mean
let other users try it
and we have revised networking
and so this
Uh came up
as a release called 4.1b
and then fairly quickly thereafter the signal
stuff got cleaned up
and so 4.1b got replaced with 4.1c
Uh remember there were four things that we need
to get done so A was the networking B was the file system
and C was the signalling and
D was supposed to be
the virtual memory which of course didn't happen
for another six or seven years
Uh but
at any rate 4.1c was another one
of these ones
which was an enormously picked up
very wide distribution
uh and in
in the meantime
Uh you know the folks at the BBN continued
working and developing and
polishing their code
uh but Bill had asked another copy
of it so
they hadn’t delivered it because it
wasn’t done yet any way
uh and they’re just get it done
then give it to Berkeley we could put it
in this
preparation for shipping 4.2
Well 4.1c got out there
and uh
Bill then was setting about to work on
the VM stuff
When one day going to his office to
chat with him. He says, “Come into my office"" and he says
""you know I
I am
involved with these other folks down at Stanford
and they have some hardware
and they want
me to put some Berkeley UNIX on it
and you know
start selling these things as workstations
and uh
I’m going I gonna go
I am going down there to be one of the
founding members of this and you should come
along
uh because you know
you being a single digit
employee at workstations.
You’ll get huge stock option
it’s gonna be really exciting"" and you know
I at that time I had already completed my degree
in business from
Uh University California so
I knew something about business
in fact I had taken an entrepreneurial course
so I knew a lot about starting up companies
or so I thought.
And so I said,” Well you know Bill
this all sounds good what you know what what
is that’s going to make you so successful.”
He says, ”It's the gact that you know we're
not going to vendor lock in and you know it's going
to be running the UNIX and
if SUN doesn’t do it right they can always go to
another vendor and can get UNIX from them.""
and uh that’s that's going to be the story
And I said, “Well you know this is well and good but
let me explain about workstations”
Uh workstations is about the install base of applications
because people buy workstations because the applications
run on it
And uh you know this is company APPOLO that had
a 4 year head start on SUN and they've
got a lock on the applications
and people aren’t going to switch to SUN because
they need the applications that run on APPOLO.
So you know
I'm sure it's going to be interesting but
uh
you know I'm only a few months from finishing
my PhD and I know if I go to a SUN with you that
won't happen
So I’m gonna my PhD we'll see how SUN is doing in
over six or eight months and you know
We’ll evaluate""
well of course it took me fourteen
fifteen months to finish my PhD and of
course by that time
SUN had burst onto the scene and didn't
have any particularly interesting stock options
left
So uh if you want it buy yourself a business perhaps
I'm not the one to ask
at any rate
Bill left without doing the VM system
Uh and he took 4.1c with him to get it
ported on to the SUN hardware.
and
with this sort uh of hit
on the main developer
uh we decided that rather than trying up to get
someone else up to speed in getting to the
VM done and so on.
That we would instead
just declare the first three pieces of this
4 piece contract
uh worth releasing
and so
uh around this time
this would be about June of 1983
Uh Micheal Karl joins the group
essentially coming in uh
to replace in into the position that was
up formerly held by
Sam ..Sam uh out by
Bill as that sort of
Head of lead programmer
uh and
because Sam also Sam had also considered taking
that position but ultimately decided that
uh he he didn't want to do that he was gonna
to go off to do graphics at
Lucasfilm
and so
the uh
the upshot of this was that
4.2 got released
in about August of '83
And uh
there’re uh about 1000 copies around remember for each
copy that goes out that’s like an institution gets
a copy and you know
spread across all their machines et cetera.
Uh there's another way of looking at it is you can
look at the number of licenses that AT&T
had outstanding
and how many licenses that Berkeley had
at the time we had shipped a thousand, there were
about twelve hundred
uh AT&T licenses. So it says that
fair number of people were running
Uh now at this point just for context AT&T is
releasing system 5 release 1
So that is short of where they are.
Uh They had taken their file system and
upped the block size from 512 bytes
to 1K
Uh at any rate
BBN
was very upset that their TCP/IP
had not been incorporated.
and here we had released it but it was this like
prototype early version had been bastardized
by Bill
and like you know this isn't it that you know
DARPA paid and now you know have the shiny wonderful
TCP/IP stack.
You should be putting this in
and so
they began agitating with DARPA and saying
what you know Blah Blah get this to happen
and so
uh Michael Karels being the very deliberative
what a person he is.
Says Ok well
I'll take the TCP/IP code from BBN and I'll
take the TCP code from
that we have in 4.2
and I'll evaluate both of them
and the evaluation involves you know
performance and maintain ability
and functionality and all these various
necessary things
and
He says, “ Well you know the TCP/IP the idea comes
from BBN and has some really good ideas
that we don't have so we'll just
Pick those up and drop it in our distribution
Uh but we don't really feel that their
code is uh you know
is the good place to start from. There's a lot of people
this point
that have worked with the Berkeley code and they know
that code base there have been a huge amount of enhancements
on it.
Uh This is wonderful book that's been written
all about it
So it is very well documented
and
it just doesn't seem to have really make sense
to
reset back to here and then have to get all
of those improvements changes et cetera.
Uh into this
particular new version.
uh it it
I finally graduated in '84 and joined
the project
uh foolishly that taking over as
it's technically but
is the lead
which meant that I got to deal with all of
the political bullshit while
Mike and others got to do lots of programming
So let that be a lesson to you that if you think
that they're trying to sweet talk
you and how great it is to be in-charge
of things.
Uh
At any rate we
continue debating back and forth about this
stuff with BBN.
We kept taking stuff and putting it into
And look you know that and say that ""We've taken that we've
we’ve taken that""
“No No. You have to take the code
You got to take the code.”
So at any rate 4.3
was really designed
much like 4.1 in the sense of consolidating
what we already had. So throughout the eh
the even-numbered releases from Berkeley had
a lot of new functionality and odd releases
tried to really get the performance up
Uh we we're always striving to make sure that
things worked when the released it, but we didn't
always
strive to make sure they ran optimally.
Uh figuring that it was better to sort of
tune things
after the fact once you had a electrode working
in right way.
So anyway we made an announcement
of 4.3
Uh actually at the June 1985
UNIX conference, so two years basically have
gone by here.
and
uh
BBN
you know immediately objects that we have
not taken their code
and
uh they go to DARPA
and they said, “Look ,you paid BBN
how many millions of dollars, more than you paid to
Berkeley to do this code
you're gonna uh you know
and now they're not taking it
and and you know
you got look like ninnies or something.” I
don't know
I don’t know what they’ve
said I wasn't there
But at any rate
DARPA
representative shows up in my office
and
Uh very calmly
uh explains that.
You know
the agreement was that BBN was going to do the
TCP/IP code and
Uh Berkeley was to do the interface
and
This is this is the way the world and
you know we appreciate that you know you’ve
done other stuff and it was it was great work
but
they are funding us and this is the way it is.
And my quarrel is like
uh you know Mike Karels is arguing with them and look,
you know we've taken this and we’ve
put over here, all the reasons that I gave earlier
and you know the guy finally at the end just
says,
“ No, you don't understand.
We're in charge
this is what you doing. Goodbye!""
And you know
it just doesn't work very well at Berkeley
just come in and say,
“This is what you're going to do.”
The free speech movement comes to mind.
Uh so
You know Mike in particularly just goes completely BANANAS.
Goes off, “Aggarh”
and then fires off
unannounced to me fires off the thing
that the DARPA uh
which if I'd been would keep in shut
because I would not let them blame SUN
At any rate
I mean I only see it because DARPA guy
sent it back to me and says you need to keep
your staff under control.
Uh so
at any rate um you know
Mike just says, “I'm not doing it.
They can't make me, I'll just leave.”
You know so you know
You tell them that they can either this way or
they can have that way or we won’t release it. Um
Agrh . um
Come on there’s got to be some compromise
we can do here.
So
Finally uh I say, “Okay let’s I
I propose that we have a bake-off.
So we will uh we we had already incorporated
into there was big switch so you could compile ot
way or the other
So my first proposal was
we will just ship it
with a compile time options.
So you can compile for BBN code
or you could compile it for Berkeley code.
Even BBN
Even DARPA could see
this was a no-win
because you’ll end up with some
people running one some people running the
other, this won’t work smoothly.
This was just not
where they want it to go.
and so we said, “Okay well
switch is there it's really easy to compile
the two different systems.
Let’s have a bake-off
you know we’ll compile
with one and compiler with other one and have bunch of
tests
and you know will decide which one is better.
Well of course we're not going to let
Berkeley do the testing because they'd be biased
for Berkeley. We’re not going to let BBN to do the testing
because they’ll be biased for BBN.
so we’ve to find a
uh
a third party and
uh the third party that DARPA actually proposes
is a guy named Mike Moose at the Ballistics
Research Laboratory, just up the road from
here and
Uh yeah
little known to
most of the people is that we actually knew Mike Moose
very well because we had interacted a whole lot with him.
working on TCP/IP
so
we’re like uhm yah it’s ok with us.
And you know he was in military you know
chain of command and BBN muck-a-mucks
new ones so
they’re fine with it
So ok great so
you know off we ship that tape and
He does not tell us what tests he is gonna run
so neither side gets to
do anything other than make some suggestions
general suggestions so
Of course we suggest the 3 port performance
test could be important
and the BBN suggests that
uh how well it works in the face of large
package
rate losses is important
because of course the military you know will drop
a nuclear bomb on Chicago we want to make sure
it drops down through Dallas
At any rate Mike Moose sets up these the systems
and
runs a bunch of tests
and of course without talking to either side
and so we're sort of pins and needles
because you know several weeks goes by
and finally duh
his report lands.
You know humh comes in the mail here's his report
And the first thing you’d do is
to flip to the last page to see what the conclusion
is but he knew that's what we're going to
do so he hid the conclusion somewhere in the
middle
Forcing you to read the entire thing
but it's a it's a very interesting week because
in terms of the throughput
as expected we did better
Uh what
that he introduced a thing where it would
randomly drop about every
fourth package
and
under this scenario
he says uh
the BBN code
Jumps out to an early start getting a lot
more data through in the face of high
packet loss uh
but but the Berkeley part managers to catch up
while the BBN machine reboots.
Uh
Ultimately resulting in the conclusion
that even in the face of the packet
loss, Berkeley code seems to
do a little better.
And uh so his
conclusion is that it should continue to ship
with the BSD code.
Uh so with this result in hand
we are authorized by DARPA to do the release
and we finally managed to release
4.3 in June of
so
at this point uh
At this point
the new TCP code is gone out
or you know that
The revised BSD TCP code has gone out
[with or without subnets]
With or without uh..subnets
uh that had
well the class ABC type of subnets
not
not the uh
the sider stuff
sider came along
okay
uh at any rate uh
now we start accelerating the story a bit again
because I have to finish in
eight minutes
so at this point
Keith Bostic
comes to
comes to Berkeley
uh he had been at Seismo which some of you
may know
and this is in the fall of 1986 so
we've released 4.3 we’re just
getting cranked up
to work on 4.4 um
remember that VM thing
and I think by this time there is this other little
protocol MFS you may’ve heard of it
and it was felt that we ought to have that
as well
uh so bring Keith Bostic on board and
Uh one of his of requirements for coming
is that we have to agree to allow him to finish
that port of
2.11 to the PDP 11 uh
and uh you know
it's it's a real challenge to get a kernel which
at that point was about
just under 200 kilobyte of text
to fit on to a machine that has a maximum
amount of program space of 64 kilobytes
because what you have to do is to
break it into overlays
and then you map in the overly and
the granularity of mapping is 4k
okay
So there's only eight pieces that you
can remap uh
Mike and my attitude was that’s an
incredibly challenging problem and it's
probably you know intellectually very stimulating
but there's no way how we would do that.
Well if you want to do it you know
by all means you can do that in your
spare time
uh there is only three jobs you need to do
uh one is uh you need to be to answer the
phone
uh first things other than distributions like
technical questions
and answer the incoming email stream for technical
questions.
Uh do some programming and in in your spare
time you can work on the PDP 11
and no he was
had no other support for the phones and the
email
and we had
you know by this time about two thousand
uh distributions
So at any rate Keith did in fact finally
finish the PDP 11.
Uh port uh
got 2.11 out of the door
and we have a party to celebrate the fact
that he had completed this.
and part of the party was opening the window
on the fourth floor
of our uh building
and taking his PDP 11 and
ceremoniously dropping out of the window to the cement
sidewalk four stories below
to ensure that he would never
work on it again.
This was him doing this not us.
At any rate uh
Keith of course being in the front line
uh support
Uh had a lot of feedback from various users uh
in particular
there were a number of vendors that were
trying to build
uh
These network cards you could plug into a PC
that would provide TCP/IP networking
and of course the PC it was way too feeble
to actually run the code in the PC itself
so they had a outward
processor on the card
and they’d put the TCP/IP in there
that would sort of look
uh like a
file or some kind of device on
the PC and
so they would just open this thing
get connected to the network
and So of course they wanted TCP/IP
code from Berkeley along with the important
utilities like O or Rlogin and
RCP uh
by that time finally FTP and TELNET uh
and
they didn't, our standard thing was
just buy the distribution and take whatever
they need to get out of it.
But that meant they had to get an AT&T license.
By the late 80’s the AT&T
licenses or up to like a quarter million dollars
and when you're in a little
commodity PC business a quarter million dollar
cost just to get the software before you do
anything with it
was just a non-starter for them.
And so we're getting requests for just
that TCP/IP code and associated utilities.
clearly since it all been developed in Berkeley
was none of that in the original version 7 UNIX
that we started from uh
AT&T couldn’t lay any claim to that.
And so we talked to the lawyers at Berkeley and
they’re like this “How can we make money on this?” uh
because that's what they were paid to say and
so we pointed out to them that it had been developed
under a government contract and we showed them
the government contract saying that you know
this stuff done in this contract has to be
made
available to the public at reasonable cost or
whatever it said
and uh
so
it didn’t really say that but be convinced the
lawyers that it did
and so
They agreed to lead us to pull out
this chunk of Berkeley code and we
released that
under
this new license that the lawyers cooked up
uh which is the one that we today think of
as the BSD license.
And of course our goal was to the absolutely
as
free as you know free to give away as we could possibly
could the really only thing you had to do was to give due credit
to Berkeley.
Uh so this was networking release 1.
and uh it was a wild success
uh the amazing thing was that we sold at 100
we could
Buy it from Berkeley for 1000 dollars
or you could just downloaded it off UUNet
for free
and yet a thousand people chose to pay a 1000
dollars at Berkeley to get it.
and the only difference was that you got
to take a 9 track tape which many people didn't
have any way of reading
and
uh
that a piece of paper signed by the Berkeley
lawyers
essentially saying “Yes you can use this”
and that's what they were paying a 1000 dollars for
and the lawyers of course got paid something
like a hundred dollars for every one of
these that they signed because of the overhead
et cetera
they thought this was the cat's pyjamas
you know maybe the campus was making a lot of
money but their office was doing just fine Thank
you very much!
so
Uh at any rate oh
That one was
widely successful
and so there was pressure and Keith
would come inside uh someone today wants VI or somebody
wants this is or somebody
wants that
and you know we really ought to do this and uh
you know how about figuring out other parts of the
kernel.
Mike and I would
Michael and I would look at the each other we
look at Keith it’s like yah yah all right.
Uh what you figured out you know I mean
You know all entire of the C library and all
this and that
so we got to the conferences and
Keith is
putting up you know these huge list of utilities
you’ll rewrite this utility and get your name
in lights.
and uh you know and uh
So he would get this stuff sent in to him
and he would almost always just take a
bash it in Keith normal form which
usually did look a lot like what he got but
he started from clean so that
Was uh
you know good and you know it was sort of easy
you know that first someone sends in cat in.
you know someone like really go ho hog and
does that all options to LS
this is in the days before GNU software
you know
lots of options were invoked
Uh and then
one day uh
Keith comes into to report
that somebody is redoing
the TRaw family
and this is when Mike and I look at each
sort of gulp
because the next question out of
Keith’s mouth is ""How’s that kernel coming guys?""
We can't go to the UNIX conferences and say rewrite
the kernel to get your name in lights you know
so we actually have to like go through and
figure out what's
Berkeley and what's not Berkeley and
segregate stuff out uh
A long story but eventually we get
something we feel that was clean
and uh so
we go back to the lawyers and say we
got this little update to the networking tape
that we'd like to do
uh that uh we're going to call it networking
release 2 Net 2 and
so actually
we do sort of come on and explain it is practically
the entire system and
lots of stuff happens but they finally sign
off on it
and we put it out there
and it's out there for good half a year before
BSDi
sort of fills in the missing bits and starts selling
it
they you know
engineers are
not really that good at
marketing and so
in particular they think that the sort of
cutesy things like
having your phone number being 1800
itsUNIX
and adds to save a ninety nine percent of the
price of a AT&T charges for source code
Uh are cute
But it really irritates
the piss out of AT&T
And so they sue us
imagine that why they sue BSDi
and BSDi is what added only these 6
files and you know all the rest came from Berkeley.
So we would be happy to talk about any of
the six files you’d like to
uh but otherwise you know forget it
and the judge agrees
because they don't have any problem about
those six files and so
there's no choice but to sue the University
and uh
that’s another long story in which I did
become an expert witness
which is actually proven
to be a relatively lucrative thing because
being an expert witness
it's something that you
it's really hard to break into that because
one wants to hire someone hasn't done it before
and it turns out that it really didn't
matter how much you know, do
you have a PhD because if you have PhD by definition
you must know you're talking about
I'm not making this up.
and number two is
How you speak in public then you know especially
people harassing you, well I've had ten thousand
students you know
there's not a question that a graduate student
has never asked me that I hadn't dealt with,
and lawyer is not up to a graduate student.
So I did pretty well that score too
uh and so
because I that they were forced to use me
in this case.
And but I did ran after then
the lawyer the outside lawyer that the Berkeley
got me to do some other stuff and
one thing leads to another so today I am uh
an expert in the
network compliance vs SUN microsystem
lawsuit vs ZFS lawsuit
which is uh
an interesting story that you can ask over
beer
At any rate
we eventually win the lawsuit
And uh and we don't win it we settle the
lawsuit excuse me I have to use proper terminology
here.
We have to agree
that networking release 2 did in fact have
things in it that infringed
uh and
however
Uh the things that infringe were sufficiently
minor that with some
changes
uh we can
get something that's clean
we agreed that we will re-release
we'd do new release that has all these
changes made in it as 4.4 BSD lite.
So it’s 4.4 BSD which is the whole
thing complete with AT&T stuff and the
AT&T licenses
and for 4.4 BSD lite
which is got the stuff, the AT&T stuff stripped out
of it.
And AT&T really thought they’d won big-time
because all these people had been using the
Net 2.
They're going to be forced to throw it out
because we’re not allowed to tell what the changes
were
and have to start all over again
from lite
And the Bill Jolitz in particular just never did that
and so that's why this distribution got hammered
FreeBSD had to do it
the NetBSD folks had to do it uh
and it was a huge amount of work but they
did it
and it was great because we got two more years
worth of our technology out
at any rate, that,
we actually did one more incremental sort of the
release, like 2
I would just fix some of the most egregious
bugs
that’s what all happened was we got all these people
who bought this BSD lite licenses
Because they wanted to pay the
thousand dollars to get the piece of paper
saying
and this one's fine too
and uh
so we had a chunk of money and so Keith
and I just sort of worked
through that money
and it's just spend it
essentially doing bug fixes and stuff on lite
And finally released when the money ran out then
we left the university and that was the last release
Uh from from Berkeley
and that is the end of my story
So any questions?
Uh .. Yes
Sorry.. uh VM system
VM system yes.
So the VM system was actually sort of an interesting
story uh..
Actually both VM and NFS were interesting
Stories.
The VM system uh
one of our attitudes was that why always come
up with a good idea when you can steal a better
one and
you know it's just a lot of work to write
a VM system this uh
you know that BSD folks
clearly know
and
uh so
we looked around to see if there's anything
that we could use
rather than have to write it from the scratch
ourselves, and
evaluated two different things. One
was
uh the stuff that SUN had done
and the other was the stuff that had been done at
Carnegie Mellon under the Mach thing and
Uh they've done a whole lot of very good work
on the VM system we didn't really agree with
the micro-kernel principle but we liked
the VM system
and so we talked to SUN about potentially
Contributing uh
chunk of their VM system we talked to them
about contributing a chunk of their
VFS stuff.
We knew that we couldn’t get NFS from them but
they they you know
the folks at SUN sorts of in engineering were too
enthusiastic about it and percolated it all the way
up to the Scott McNealy, he was the CEO at that
time
and even Scott McNealy was pretty enthusiastic about
giving the stuff to Berkeley.
you know as long as SUN would get credit for
it
And uh
so it really got to the point where it
is needed to be signed off by the SUN
lawyers
and so they sent it off to them and after that SUN
lawyers came back and said,
“Well you know your stock holders could accuse you of
giving away company property
and and sue you in court and we really don't
recommend that you do this.”
and so
that the very last minute it was ..
We couldn't get any of that stuff from SUN.
So we ended up
adopting this stuff from Mach
the Mach VM system
and
so it fell to myself to take that and
figure out essentially how to plug it in.
and the problem was the old VM system
was very portable provided you were porting
into something that looked a lot like a VAX.
because it came down to uh you know the that the
basic page data structure was the VAX
page data structure.
and so when people would port it.
If they have something with the page data structure
to look different they wouldn't take it from
the VAX and they'd shuffle the bits around and put
it in the right order and then dropped it into
the whatever that architecture was
a page table. So it worked pretty well for porting
into the Motorola uh because the
MMU network was a lot like the VAX
uh
and some other machines but in other ways it
just really didn't cut it at all
whereas the VM had been done by
the the folks at CMU.
In Mach was uh you know
very elegantly designed
uh and in fact
it had in some ways
too many bells and whistles and too many options
and because a lot of sort of dead ends they
just sort of left hanging there
Uh but uh
the structure itself was nicely done about it was
about 90% machine independent code
10 % machine dependent code so that
a well defined interface.
the PMAC interface.
and so got that put in and of course we
did it onto the Berkeley MMAP Interface
rather than what they did
with uh ports and so on
Uh and
So I got that together sort in the that
the 4.3 phase I didn’t talk about there were
two releases between 4.3 and 4.4
4.3
Tahoe and 4.3 Reno and
the first of them having the VM and the
second one having the NFS in it.
And uh
so
that got put out and then luckily people would feel
sort of look at it and said well you know
this really needs like a lot of work
so Mike Hibler, at the University of Utah did a tremendous
amount of the clean up in it.
and then later actually after we release
lite BSD in agreement
David Greenman did a whole lot more work on it.
really were just throwing tons of shit out
that shouldn’t have been at first place.
I had this whole notion of an external user
driven pager which was nice but the cost
of all the extra context switching other
things that would happen on pagefault was sort of
a killer uh
And so at any rate that's that's how the the
VM system got in there.
Any more questions?
See I can take like five minutes to answer
one question.
All right! Well Thank You very much.